Greesham Anand, SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

Ga.greeshamanand@gmail.com | https://github.com/GreeshamAnand

Profile

Data Science professional with 5+ years of work experience delivering value in Fortune 500 Companies. 2+ years of Data Science experience working on wide array of datasets solving business problems to improve revenue and providing innovative digital solutions.

Industry Experience

CUMMINS INC, 2018 - Present

Senior Data Scientist, Jun 2018 - Present

- Led a team of Data Scientist to develop Range Estimation model from POC to production deployment for EV Transit bus, getting accuracy to >95%
 - o Deployed Algorithm in production-ready Python Package using functional, defensive programming
 - o Created and documented Functional Excellence Practices while developing the algorithms
- Develop a Fault Isolation Model to identify components which are failing by combining multiple datasets using **Clustering and Classification Algorithms** leading to potential savings of \$700K/yr.
- Develop a Warranty recovery model as Tech Lead to collect Warranty \$ from suppliers of Claim Parts leading to potential annual savings of \$7.2m +
- Research and Develop Wisdom of Crowd algorithm to identify parameters responsible for failure of engines on Time series data
 - O Solution written in **pyspark** in a scalable fashion to enable usage with multiple datasets.
- Worked on Maintenance Scheduling project for external vendor and identified points of improvement to create better preventive maintenance schedule leading to tangible annual savings of \$110.6K
- Developed a **Micro Transit Vehicle Estimation model** for Purdue University to predict the future passenger load using multiple modes of public transit and vehicle size and wait time using Machine learning and Queuing theory.

Intern, Reliability Engineer, Cummins Inc. Jun 2017 - Aug 2017

- Reduced work hours for job by 98% be developing an algorithm to text mine Fault codes using **Natural** Language Processing, TFIDF which is being used across functions saving millions.
- Implemented **Bayesian statistical model** to improve the Reliability planner and improved visibility calculations for better decision making leading to potential savings.

TATA MOTORS LTD. October 2013 - May 2013

Assistant Manager, Tata Motors Ltd, October 2013 - May 2016

- Created **statistical models** and improved the engine performance by 25% without worsening emission norms by analyzing complex multi-dimensional data for engine optimization using R.
- Converted Data Analysis into real world changes improving efficiency leading to faster product development.

SKILLS

Software: Python, Scala, Pyspark, R, SQL, Azure Databricks, PostgreSQL

Visualization: Seaborn, Plotly Matplotlib, ggplot, R-shiny

Packages: scikitlearn, keras, pandas, numpy, scipy, TensorFlow, ArcGIS

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN

M.S in Operations Research and Industrial Engineering 3.76/4.0 August 2016 – May 2018

DELHI TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY (Formerly DCE)

B.Tech in Automotive Engineering 3.75/4.0 August 2009 – May 2013

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Q3 2019 Digital Star Award
- Q4 2019 Digital Star Award
- Leadership Badge 2019 for Micro Transit Project.
- Amongst Top 0.6% (531) out of 90,000 in Xavier's Aptitude Test 2015.







Decognition

Greesham Anand

DIGITAL STAR AWARD – Q3, 2019
For invaluable contribution in support of DA Innovations Projects

David Leach

Executive Director Analytics & Artificial Intelligence



Recognition

Greesham Anand

DIGITAL STAR AWARD – Q3, 2019
For invaluable contribution in support of DA Innovations Projects

David Leach

Executive Director Analytics & Artificial Intelligence